{"tossups": [{"question": "During this battle, Ulu\u00b8c [oo-looch] Ali was able to capture the standard of the Knights Hospitaller. The Genoese admiral Andrea Doria fought in this battle after a defeat at the Battle of Preveza. Six powerful galleasses were provided by Venice to this battle\u2019s winning side, which was commanded by Don John, the brother of the Holy Roman Emperor Philip II. For ten points, name this decisive 1571 naval victory for a Christian alliance, stopping the Ottoman advance into the Mediterranean Sea.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Lepanto</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Major John Brown\u2019s failure to reinforce this man\u2019s army in time resulted in Guy Carleton\u2019s capture of this man at the Battle of Longue-Pointe. The day before Seth Warner took Fort Crown Point, this man and Benedict Arnold led a successful capture of a fort whose weapons helped end the Siege of Boston. Fort Ticonderoga was captured by, for ten points, what leader of Vermont\u2019s Green Mountain Boys?", "answer": "Ethan<b> Allen</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A myth relates how this location was created after a king performed a thousand years of penance to break a curse on 60,000 brothers who had been incinerated. Millions of people journeyed to this location in February 2013 as part of a Kumbh Mela pilgrimage whose final destination was in Allahabad. Waters in this location are said to have purifying powers because they have touched Vishnu\u2019s feet. For ten points, name this sacred river of Hinduism.", "answer": "<b> Ganges</b> River (accept<b> Ganga</b>; accept<b> Allahabad</b> before read; prompt on India and/or Bangladesh before \u201criver\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "As Chancellor of the Exchequer, this politician introduced a budget that included the Cobden-Chevalier Treaty, lowering Anglo-French tariffs. As Prime Minister, he was able to secure the passage of a bill which benefited Irish tenants, but was never able to secure home rule during his four terms. This man\u2019s Midlothian Campaign attacked his rival, a Conservative politician with a close friendship with Queen Victoria. For ten points, name this Liberal Prime Minister who feuded with Benjamin Disraeli.", "answer": "William Ewart<b> Gladstone</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This building was the site of an infamous jump by Franz Reichelt, whose parachute demonstration failed. This structure was derided as a \u201cgigantic black smokestack\u201d in a petition by the \u201cArtists Protest,\u201dwhich attempted to stop its construction. Maurice Koechlin and Emile Nouguier helped design this structure, found on the Champ de Mars, for the World\u2019s Fair of 1889. For ten points, name this iconic wrought iron tower in Paris.", "answer": "<b> Eiffel Tower</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. The construction of this location at Mount Li was described by Sima Qian [chee-ahn], who noted that streams of mercury flowed through it in an attempt to recreate the Yangtze and Yellow Rivers. This location was first discovered by workers digging a well in Xiyang [shee-yahng]. To serve their master in the afterlife, thousands of terracotta warriors were placed in, for ten points, what resting place of the first emperor of unified China?", "answer": "The<b> Mausoleum of the First Qin Emperor</b> (accept descriptions of<b> Qin</b> Shi Huangdi\u2019s <b>mausoleum</b>; accept Qin<b> Shi Huang</b>di in place of \u201cQin;\u201d accept equivalents for mausoleum, such as <b>tomb</b>,<b> burial ground</b>,<b> grave</b>, etc)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This program gained support after a report by Herbert Hoover deemed it was infeasible to turn one nation into a \u201cpastoral state\u201d without the migration of 25 million people. This program, which replaced the punitive Morgenthau Plan, was announced at a Harvard commencement speech in 1947. Greece and Turkey received the first part of a disbursement of 13 billion dollars under, for ten points, what American foreign policy to help rebuild postwar Europe, named for the US Secretary of State?", "answer": "<b> Marshall Plan</b> (accept<b> European Recovery Program</b> or<b> ERP</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A medieval philosopher from this country was the first Westerner to record the formula for gunpowder in his Opus Majus. Another medieval philosopher from this country developed a \u201claw of parsimony\u201d that seeks to solve problems by working with the hypothesis with the fewest assumptions; that \u201crazor\u201d was developed by William of Ockham. For ten points, name this home country of Roger Bacon where medieval scholars studied at the University of Oxford.", "answer": "<b> England</b> (do not accept or prompt on other terms, like UK or (Great) Britain)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This organization partially titles the autobiography of its one-time leading member, George Plunkitt. This group aided the gubernatorial campaign of John Hoffman, one of its leaders known as Grand Sachems. This organization, which declined after the mayoral election of Fiorello La Guardia in 1934, achieved notoriety for its corruption and abuse of the spoils system under Boss Tweed. For ten points, name this New York City political machine.", "answer": "<b> Tammany Hall</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Bob Dylan refused to appear on this show when network officials asked him to not play \u201cTalkin\u2019 John Birch Paranoid Blues.\u201d This show displayed the caption \u201cSORRY GIRLS, HE\u2019S MARRIED\u201d on February 9, 1964. Charles Laughton filled in as host of this show on the first night that this show featured Elvis Presley, although this show\u2019s cameramen zoomed in to avoid broadcasting Elvis\u2019s provocative dancing. For ten points, name this CBS show that ran until 1971 and which drew over 70 million viewers for its first broadcast of The Beatles.", "answer": "The<b> Ed Sullivan</b> Show", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {}, {"question": "In one speech, this man was accused of turning ministers into marionnettes by Vladimir Purishkevich, who soon agreed to aid Prince Felix Yusupov in putting this man to death. This man rose to power after providing medical guidance to Alexandra Feodorovna [fay-oh-dor-ohv-na], but this man was eventually poisoned, beaten, shot, and then drowned by nobles who believed he had undue influence over the Romanov family. For ten points, name this Russian mystic and advisor to Nicholas II.", "answer": "Grigori<b> Rasputin</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The god Mithras is often portrayed sacrificing one of these animals in reliefs, such as one in Vienna\u2019s Kunsthistoriches Museum. A woman holding pink fabric grabs onto a swimming, white one of these animals in Titian\u2019s<em> Rape of Europa</em>. In Hindu myth, Shiva\u2019s mount is one of these animals named Nandi. Scenes from frescos found at the Palace of Knossos depict youths jumping over the horns of, for ten points, what bovine animal represented by the constellation Taurus?", "answer": "<b> bull</b>s (prompt on cows or cattle)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "Aulus Hirtius and Vibius Pansa died while fighting against this man\u2019s army, which was busy besieging Decimus Brutus at Mutina. This man, who split his territory between his children in the Donations of Alexandria, was the third and final husband of Fulvia. In 31 BC, this man fled from the Battle of Actium after the retreat of his lover, Cleopatra. For ten points, name this protege of Julius Caesar who lost a civil war to Octavian.", "answer": "<b> Mark Antony</b> (or<b> Marcus Antonius</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A leader of one of these organizations, Dave Beck, pled the Fifth Amendment when he was called to testify in front of the McClellan Committee. Voting procedures in these organizations are governed by the Landrum-Griffin Act. Agreements whereby people vowed not to join these organizations, or yellow dog contracts, were outlawed by the Norris-LaGuardia Act. For ten points, name these organizations that may engage in collective bargaining with management on behalf of their working members.", "answer": "labor<b> union</b>s (accept<b> Teamster</b>s during the first sentence)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This river was the site of the second largest flood in geologic history, the Bonneville flood, when the Portneuf River overflowed into this river during the last ice age. This river derived its name from a misinterpreted (+) Shoshone hand signal for the nearby abundant salmon, the letter S. This river flows through Twin Falls, north of which (*) </b> Evel Knievel failed to jump across a canyon in 1974. For ten points, name this tributary of the Columbia that flows past Boise to form the northern border between Idaho and Oregon.", "answer": "<b> Snake</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>In this modern day country, Johann Beaulieu was unable to defend a bridgehead over the river Adda at Lodi [loh-dee]; this set-back, along with Joseph Alvinzci\u2019s defeat at Arcole</b> <b>[ar-co-lay] in this modern day country, ensured that the First (+)</b> <b>Coalition would have to</b> <b>accept the creation of the Ligurian Republic. Another battle in this modern day country, the Battle of (*) </b> Marengo, began when a commander led his troops atop a donkey through the St. Bernard Pass. For ten points, name this modern-day country where Napoleon crossed the Alps to score a victory near Piedmont.", "answer": "<b> Italy</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this election year, the losing ticket\u2019s vice presidential nominee developed the recurring theme of the \u201cTwo Americas;\u201d that politician then lost his position as Senator from North</b> <b>Carolina. After this election year\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Iowa caucuses, the third-place finisher shouted</b> <b>\u201cYeah!\u201d at the end of his rallying speech; that shriek by Howard Dean is largely thought to have doomed his campaign. (*)</b> Veterans used \u201cswiftboating\u201d to attack the Democratic nominee in this year. For ten points, name this year in which John Edwards and John Kerry lost to the re-election campaign of George W. Bush.", "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of<b> 2004</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In 1946, this figure noted \u201cthere is a somber point in the social outlook of Americans\u201din a lecture against racism at the historically black Lincoln University. This figure\u2019s literary rights were bequeathed to the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, which he helped establish.</b> <b>This man (+)</b> <b>signed a 1939 letter written by Leo Szilard [zee-lard] that was sent to</b> <b>signed a 1939 letter written by Leo Szilard [zee-lard] that was sent to</b> <b>President Roosevelt, warning him of the threat of (*)</b> <b>President Roosevelt, warning him of the threat of (*)</b> German nuclear bombs. For ten points, name this physicist who won a Nobel Prize for his work on the photoelectric effect and who also developed the theory of special relativity.", "answer": "Albert<b> Einstein</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this war during the breakup of Yugoslavia that included the Siege of Sarajevo.", "answer": "<b> Bosnia</b>n War (prompt on Yugoslavian War(s))", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}